<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Federal Field Notes</title>
  <subtitle>Dispatches from the front lines of Canada&#39;s federal digital transformation.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://federal-field-notes.ca/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https:/federal-field-notes.ca" />
  <updated>2022-03-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https:/federal-field-notes.ca</id>
  <author>
    <name>Paul Craig</name>
    <email>paul@pcraig3.ca</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Move fast, stay safe</title>
    <link href="https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/" />
    <updated>2022-03-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/</id>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;nav class=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#mixing-oil-and-water-planning-for-spontaneity&quot;&gt;Mixing oil and water: planning for spontaneity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#working-with-wagile&quot;&gt;Working with Wagile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#the-docs-blocker&quot;&gt;The docs blocker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#moving-fast-why-releasing-early-and-often-is-important&quot;&gt;Moving fast: why releasing early and often is important&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#being-safe-why-we-dont-want-to-break-things&quot;&gt;Being safe: why we don’t want to ‘break things’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#empowered-teams-vs-oversight-committees&quot;&gt;Empowered teams vs. oversight committees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#being-safe-in-agile&quot;&gt;‘Being safe’ in agile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#2-agile-reduces-the-cost-of-mistakes&quot;&gt;2. Agile reduces the cost of mistakes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#3-agile-reduces-the-likelihood-of-mistakes&quot;&gt;3. Agile reduces the likelihood of mistakes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#4-agile-is-flexible&quot;&gt;4. Agile is flexible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#moving-faster-or-being-safer&quot;&gt;Moving faster or being safer?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#a-practical-example-launching-a-website-in-a-federal-department&quot;&gt;A practical example: launching a website in a federal department&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/nav&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Introduction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it’s all coming together. The kids are back in school, the province is re-opening, the snow is melting, and, best of all, you’re part of an agile innovation team trialling a new way of working at a Canadian federal department. Maybe you’re a “ninja team” (there’s still a couple years until you figure out why you shouldn’t call it that), or a tiger team (still okay), or maybe you just call yourselves a product team. You have the support of your &lt;abbr title=&quot;Director General&quot;&gt;DG&lt;/abbr&gt;, a handful of enthusiastic recruits, and maybe even &lt;a href=&quot;https://digital.canada.ca/2018/06/27/tools-to-do-good-work/&quot;&gt;a few off-network devices to start prototyping with&lt;/a&gt;. As long as you have at least one developer with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; account and someone who knows how Figma works (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/pricing/&quot;&gt;starter plan!!&lt;/a&gt;), you’re basically &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UHZuLMFfriQ&quot;&gt;the best of the best of the best&lt;/a&gt;. There’s just one problem: you’re going to find that ‘doing the work’ is actually only half of the work — the other half turns out to be ‘getting it approved.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your team really gets going, you’ll be producing plenty of public artefacts — journey maps, priority matrices, wireframes, open-source prototypes (with appropriate ‘this is a prototype’ labelling) — and &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/10/30/working-in-the-open-firsts-for-covid-alert/&quot;&gt;communicating openly as you go&lt;/a&gt;: either through blog posts or more casually on Twitter (preferably both!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this is the worst nightmare of a plan-first, quadruple-check-everything, launch-when-it’s-perfect enterprise department: a team releasing unvetted material to the public without going through official oversight channels, on a two-week sprint cadence that none of the committees can realistically accommodate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, someone will ask you what happens if you publish something you shouldn’t. Suppose it leads to a big media exposé, maybe even a lawsuit. You will say that that’s incredibly unlikely (and you’ll be right), but, the thing is, you’ll be talking to groups looking for the worst possible outcome. It’s like trying to convince someone that crossing the street is relatively safe and people do it all the time, only to have them keep bringing up the time a minivan hit a teenager 10 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of argument quickly becomes deadlocked because it’s a disagreement about core principles, not tactics. Ultimately, this misalignment stems from two different approaches to managing risk. Agile workflows acknowledge that all projects include some element of risk — there are always things we don’t know — and incorporate user testing and team retrospectives to fill in the gaps. In contrast, enterprise organizations are almost pathologically unable to accept risk and stuff those gaps with paperwork. Enterprise orgs find it very hard to tolerate any level of uncertainty, which is what agile workflows explicitly introduce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mixing-oil-and-water-planning-for-spontaneity&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#mixing-oil-and-water-planning-for-spontaneity&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Mixing oil and water: planning for spontaneity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enterprise planning (known as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model&quot;&gt;waterfall planning&lt;/a&gt;”) tries to manage large projects by creating 4-year plans that are out of date after 4 months. How does an agile team handle planning 4 years in advance? Well, typically they don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#four-years-note&quot; id=&quot;four-years-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;It’s almost impossible to guess where you will be in 4 years&lt;/a&gt;, but it’s easy to predict where you will be in a month or two. Agile planning prioritizes more immediate goals — eg, planning out your work in 2-week &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/agile/scrum/sprints&quot;&gt;sprints&lt;/a&gt; — and uses ‘impressionistic’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/agile/product-management/roadmaps&quot;&gt;roadmaps&lt;/a&gt; for longer-term projections. While the enterprise instinct is always to paper over uncertainty, agile processes embrace it: changing requirements are a part of product development and agile teams are comfortable with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, however, trading inaccurate plans for what appears to be ‘no plan at all’ doesn’t exactly look like an improvement from the perspective of a department that relies entirely on .PDF diagrams and .DOCX files to ship software. Everyone knows that &lt;abbr title=&quot;Information technology&quot;&gt;IT&lt;/abbr&gt; projects take too long and there is too much paperwork involved, but let’s not throw the bathwater out with the rest of the bathwater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To try and square this circle, enterprise orgs often come up with ‘hybrid’ models: incorporating some ‘agile’ flexibility into their traditional rigid planning processes (known as “Wagile”, from “waterfall” + “agile”). On a previous team I worked on, the enterprise security process meant completing 8 or so documents in a defined sequence: first 1, then 2, then 3, etc. Under the new “(w)agile security” process, we were instead asked to write them all simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an agile team, you should be iterating as you learn and reducing administrative overhead to focus on actually building a product. That’s all good, as long as you make sure to iterate towards a clearly-documented end-state, and fill out all the same paperwork in less time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;working-with-wagile&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#working-with-wagile&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Working with Wagile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is ‘Wagile’ a good idea? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pluralsight.com/blog/it-ops/move-away-from-wagile&quot;&gt;No&lt;/a&gt;. But how about starting fights with a bunch of people you work with and eventually having your project cancelled? Well, obviously that’s worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with your really smart critique of the status quo, you’re never going to be the only game in town. Every consultant and internal strategy group jockeying for funding will have a plan promising better outcomes for less money. As a ‘digital innovation’ team in an enterprise org, you are competing against a number of possible futures. The advantage that you have is that agile Actually Works™ — but this is a starting point, not a guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agile teams are the real deal. Some of today’s largest companies got to where they are because agile workflows are really good at quickly delivering value, beating out more established companies with slower delivery models. Under ideal conditions — supportive management, experienced team members, a well-understood problem — you should be able to fly through this stuff. But even if not, you still have a significant leg up on teams that spend 30% of their time in meetings trying to figure out if all the right people were invited. The point is to play to your strengths as much as possible, but you won’t have an entirely free hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrating ‘what good looks like’ will buy you credibility in the long term, making things easier for your team and similar teams in the future. But in the short term, the only game in town is the poorly-designed Hasbro classic: “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Risk_(game)&quot;&gt;Risk&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-docs-blocker&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#the-docs-blocker&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The docs blocker&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenexmachina.com/waterfall-vs-agile-a-knowledge-problem-not-a-requirements-problem/&quot;&gt;Despite an estimated ~14% success rate&lt;/a&gt;, enterprise processes are viewed as ‘safe’ because the many documents produced in planning phases give the &lt;em&gt;impression&lt;/em&gt; of reducing risk. Any uncertainty requires an elaborate cover-up — large “modernization” IT projects are breeding grounds for PowerPoint decks crammed with dates that slip, cost estimates that increase, and features that never materialize. Paradoxically, while this culture of misleading documentation is a contributing factor for large and expensive failures, it also poses a serious obstacle to agile teams looking to improve how projects are delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/01/28/introducing-agile-to-large-organizations-is-a-subtractive-process-not-an-additive-one/&quot;&gt;It’s not easy to subtract governance processes&lt;/a&gt; in an organization hyper-sensitive to risk (“let’s &lt;strong&gt;not do&lt;/strong&gt; this documentation and still be allowed to release”). Removing something that &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; safe (even a diagram that will soon be out of date) without an equivalent replacement is a tough sell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you set a precedent for problem-free releases, your proposals for systemic interventions will look much more credible. But you can easily end up logjammed trying to release your very first product(s) by being overly hostile to existing governance processes. Even though it’s not ‘real agile’, initial products will require some amount of gritting your teeth and hammering out documentation needed to get to a release. In order to scale your approach, you need to be able to release products — which means it must be the focus for your team as well as a priority for &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#exec-note&quot; id=&quot;exec-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;your executive sponsor(s)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-fast-why-releasing-early-and-often-is-important&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#moving-fast-why-releasing-early-and-often-is-important&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Moving fast: why releasing early and often is important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK’s Government Digital Service popularized the slogan “&lt;a href=&quot;https://gds.blog.gov.uk/2013/01/06/digital-transformation-in-2013-the-strategy-is-delivery-again/&quot;&gt;the strategy is delivery&lt;/a&gt;”: advocating prototypes instead of documentation, demos instead of decks, and 2-week sprints instead of 4-year plans. Strategy documents proclaiming much and changing little are the norm in organizations with a culture of paperwork over working code, so “the strategy is delivery” emphasizes the inverse: don’t waste time building slide decks that would be better spent getting real products in front of real users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/01/10/shipping/&quot;&gt;Shipping early&lt;/a&gt; is the best argument you can make against the reality of waterfall, because, done right, you will save huge amounts of time and money. By the same token, the longer it takes you to get products built and released, the more you resemble the expensive waterfall processes you seek to replace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why you &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;move fast&lt;/strong&gt;. In general, you want to define your MVP and then test it with users as soon as possible. Enterprise planning does not have a good answer to ‘user needs’, so it is important to prioritize early user engagement. User feedback both (a) gives you insight to improve your product and (b) functions as documentation you can share internally that other teams don’t typically have. Once you are confident that your product works, focus on what you need to do to get it released. It’s far better to have a released ‘alpha’ service than a highly-polished internal prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the tradeoff with ‘fast’ is that, conventionally understood, it means compromising on safety. Oversight groups are likely to view you as risky cowpokes who want to launch first and ask questions later, while they provide a measured and impartial analysis that protects the department from potential embarrassment. This is a dangerous characterization to have applied to you in the risk-paranoid context of a large department, so you need to do what you can to guard against this perception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;being-safe-why-we-dont-want-to-break-things&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#being-safe-why-we-dont-want-to-break-things&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Being safe: why we don’t want to ‘break things’&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mark Zuckerberg coined the phrase “move fast and break things,” he wasn’t talking to teams that need approval from an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tbs-sct.gc.ca/pol/doc-eng.aspx?id=32602#secA.2&quot;&gt;Enterprise Architecture Review Board&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://qr.ae/pGLA6x&quot;&gt;“Move fast and break things”&lt;/a&gt; essentially means that you should prioritize speed over reliability: that it’s better to build and release your software super fast — even if not everything works yet or it breaks in older versions of Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is great advice for a typical startup, but in government this is exactly what we need to be careful of. Private-sector companies typically offer services that can be found elsewhere — if the Domino’s app breaks, I can still go to Pizza Pizza. But government services are often the only option people have: we can’t afford to ship code that causes someone to miss a benefit payment they rely on to pay their rent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we compare smartphone apps to typical government services, it is clear that the ‘enterprise’ culture of oversight committees and architecture boards in no way guarantees great outcomes. But the thing is, nobody defends the status quo as the best possible system — in a government context, &lt;em&gt;it’s always about what could go wrong&lt;/em&gt;. Sure, occasionally a bug makes it through our 10 different oversight committees, but imagine the plague of locusts you would invite without them. Your agile team needs to demonstrate that what you’re doing isn’t &lt;em&gt;dangerous&lt;/em&gt;. While it’s important to be fast, you also have to &lt;strong&gt;be safe&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;empowered-teams-vs-oversight-committees&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#empowered-teams-vs-oversight-committees&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Empowered teams vs. oversight committees&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Waterfall governance creates extremely long (read: impractical) timelines, which means slow and expensive product development — but they are always justified in terms of safety. The fact that a team like yours exists means there is some desire to improve existing processes, but how to go about this is rarely spelled out. Assuming you have some high-level buy-in from an executive sponsor, you are probably going to be granted &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; leeway to skip parts of the existing governance process. However, this sets up an obvious antagonistic relationship between your team and the various oversight committees, which becomes one of the primary challenges for you to manage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The less ‘enterprise’ documentation you write, the more you’ll provoke &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#docs-note&quot; id=&quot;docs-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;oversight groups who use that documentation to determine how ‘safe’ your product is&lt;/a&gt;. Oversight committees are used to teams attempting these kinds of shortcuts, and they are justifiably suspicious. To them, you are just another version of ‘let’s skip this boring governance stuff so we can ship a bunch of untested and risky software’, or — more colloquially — ‘let us skip the vegetables and go straight to dessert’. For them, it’s a question of who takes the fall: if there is a problem later on, they are likely to be blamed for not vetting you properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Real agile’ says that empowered multi-disciplinary teams should have the skills on the team needed to build what they’re building. Governments have a legal obligation to build, say, accessible services, but there’s no legal requirement that mandates a dedicated accessibility team (which is sometimes how it’s presented). Digital teams with a robust workflow can (and do) meet accessibility requirements by following best practices. (In the UK, this is how most public services are built.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the here and now though, you need to work productively with a team you are actually trying to replace (even though — really — you are just trying to do your work with minimum fuss). These groups will be apprehensive about your ‘empowered product team’ model because it is a direct challenge to current org structures. Therefore, they have an incentive to prove they are a valuable and necessary part of the IT delivery pipeline by catching you out on any mistakes you make or bugs that slip through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you are likely to be closely scrutinized for any parts of the existing process that you skip, or are asking to skip. Even with a mandate to “push back” against existing governance, you can be sure that your push back will be pushed back. Any leeway you have is likely to be rolled back if problems are discovered that would theoretically have been prevented if you didn’t get the leeway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;being-safe-in-agile&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#being-safe-in-agile&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;‘Being safe’ in agile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For agile teams, there are 3 stock responses to how you are safer than traditional linear product development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile reduces existential mistakes&lt;/strong&gt; in the design of a service: early user engagement mitigates the risk of launching a poorly performing service, something that existing governance processes do not address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile reduces the cost of mistakes&lt;/strong&gt;: frequent iteration means smaller changes more often, which means mistakes tend to be smaller and faster to repair.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile reduces the likelihood of mistakes&lt;/strong&gt; without creating governance bottlenecks: quality checks can be done far more frequently using automation than by human assessors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to these orthodox agile arguments, there is a more existential point to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agile is, above all, a flexible approach that adapts quickly&lt;/strong&gt;. Agile teams are pragmatic in solving problems for users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Point 1 has been discussed at length, so let’s look at the other 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-agile-reduces-the-cost-of-mistakes&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#2-agile-reduces-the-cost-of-mistakes&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;2. Agile reduces the cost of mistakes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk-phobic approach of trying to prevent problems by layering on committees creates a doom loop (a cycle that gets worse over time). All these layers of governance are created to prevent costly mistakes, but mistakes are now so costly &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of excessive governance. By contrast, agile product development &lt;em&gt;reduces the cost of mistakes&lt;/em&gt;. When you are in the habit of releasing daily, bugs can be fixed within hours of being identified — whereas you could be looking at 3-6 months for more traditional teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for you, enterprise organisations don’t have any tolerance at all for risk or bugs — to paraphrase one of my former security advisors, we are always just one typo away from the &lt;abbr title=&quot;Chief Information Officer&quot;&gt;CIO&lt;/abbr&gt; having to resign. Talking about how agile lets you fix stuff faster plays directly into the perception that you are blasé about shipping a higher volume of errors. This is a losing argument for you, so avoid it altogether if possible. Instead, head off this concern by focusing on a &lt;strong&gt;rigorous automated testing pipeline&lt;/strong&gt; that bakes quality into your codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-agile-reduces-the-likelihood-of-mistakes&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#3-agile-reduces-the-likelihood-of-mistakes&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;3. Agile reduces the likelihood of mistakes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional enterprise governance relies on human gating to audit products before they are released. &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#toil-note&quot; id=&quot;toil-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;This is expensive to run and hard to scale&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to go twice as fast, you need to hire twice the staff. In contrast, agile software development seeks to replace this bottleneck with automated tests a computer can perform, usually in a matter of seconds. Automated tests are fast and give consistent feedback: they can be re-run for every single change to a codebase, whereas a human assessor responsible for many products might only have time to check once every several hundred changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very common for security documentation to be out of date — once written, it describes how the system &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; to work — whereas automated tests are up-to-date by definition. By prioritizing, as much as possible, automated over manual testing, software can be safely released multiple times per day instead of a handful of times per year without sacrificing quality. Skeptics will argue that more releases means more problems, but a comprehensive automated testing pipeline allows you to demonstrate that your way of working is actually &lt;em&gt;safer&lt;/em&gt; than the current baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even with a comprehensive suite of tests, you still need to engage with oversight groups who will expect you to go through the same steps as other teams. From their perspective, they are responsible for deciding if your product is safe or not, and just because you have built your own competing set of checks (which — big surprise — you managed to pass), it doesn’t exempt you from the ‘official’ process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-agile-is-flexible&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#4-agile-is-flexible&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;4. Agile is flexible&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#long-term-oversight-as-bureaucratic-cement&quot;&gt;As I have previously written&lt;/a&gt;, enterprise departments give oversight groups authority over product teams. If an oversight group takes issue with something, they can advise against a particular product going ahead until specific conditions are met. Sometimes, senior executives will disregard this and just launch anyway, but most of the time a negative recommendation is enough to block a product’s release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional oversight teams ask product teams for extensive written documentation about how their system works and is administered. It’s very common that this documentation goes quickly out of date and no longer describes the reality of the system. Agile practitioners call this “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Security_theater&quot;&gt;security theatre&lt;/a&gt;:” creating lots of documentation that, although it looks impressive, does not really guarantee a more secure final product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern digital organizations will bias in favour of the teams doing the work, assuming that they have more context and are in a better position to make decisions about their product. However, this is not the reality of agile teams in government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In government, oversight teams are able to block other product teams. Can they block yours? It’s probably not clear (you’re on a new team with an executive sponsor, maybe it will go ahead anyway), but at minimum you are looking at delays while everyone tries to figure out what happens next. Getting stalled undercuts your ability to &lt;strong&gt;move fast&lt;/strong&gt;, which is one of your advantages as an agile team. If adhering to agile orthodoxy leads to getting in fights with other groups, you could end up taking just as long as other teams while also generating a lot of conflict along the way — a much worse result than traditional teams that play by the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the tenets of agile is adopting pragmatic approaches that keep you moving forward. ‘&lt;strong&gt;Be safe&lt;/strong&gt;’ is as much about perception as it is about empirical results. After all, enterprise processes are assumed to be safe even when they consistently lead to poor outcomes. By buckling down and writing documentation, you buy yourself goodwill &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you increase your perception of safe conduct. That’s not to say you need to write all the documents you are asked to, just that you should pick your battles. You only have so much political capital as a new team with no track record — your immediate priority should be to &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; that track record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-faster-or-being-safer&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#moving-faster-or-being-safer&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Moving faster or being safer?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To recap, the two important considerations for agile teams in large enterprises are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivering value quickly, which means getting something into the hands of users rapidly, without spending years in planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managing (perceived) risk, which means guarding against mistakes and filling out forms when it’s expedient&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams that &lt;strong&gt;move fast&lt;/strong&gt; optimize for velocity and build quickly. Teams that &lt;strong&gt;are safe&lt;/strong&gt; take their time, focusing on testing pipelines and sometimes writing large documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two points appear to be in tension with each other. If you want maximum velocity, don’t write any tests. Just write code, ship it, and test it in production by having real users find bugs. On the other hand, if you want maximum safety, never release anything. &lt;a href=&quot;https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/roll-safe&quot;&gt;Software that never gets launched, never gets hacked&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where should you come down on the ‘fast’ vs. ‘safe’ continuum? To answer this, figure out what you are up against. You don’t need to be at ‘maximum velocity,’ you just need to beat some of the slowest development timelines on earth. Plenty of internal strategy groups will be advocating some version of Ford’s “faster horses,” saying things like: ‘we can make this 2-year process take 22 months’. You don’t need to be lightning fast, you just need to improve on existing expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-practical-example-launching-a-website-in-a-federal-department&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#a-practical-example-launching-a-website-in-a-federal-department&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;A practical example: launching a website in a federal department&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/&quot;&gt;In a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote about launching a citizen-engagement website in a federal department, so let’s take that as an example. Sure, it set some important precedents for the department (open source project, public prototypes, user research, etc), but as a technical product, it wasn’t that complex. Working full-time, it’s the kind of thing you could build in 3-4 weeks with a small team. But it didn’t take us 3-4 weeks, it took us 5 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just looking at that timeline, you might be like “wow Paul, that sucks,” which would be rude of you to say, but it’s a fair critique. Here’s the thing though, it’s still twice as fast as the typical 1-year turnaround time that the department is used to. We could have launched it sooner if we hadn’t had to write all that documentation and skimped on writing tests, but even with all that stuff we shot past our competition. Admittedly, we paid a heavy tax burden if you look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#internal-words&quot;&gt;all the writing we had to do&lt;/a&gt;, but it got the job done. In the end, rather than getting into an imbroglio about documentation as ‘security theatre,’ it was easier to just write the damn things, get them reviewed, and get the site out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were just one team, we were brand new in the department, and we were using an approach people weren’t familiar with. We didn’t have the authority or credibility to change existing processes or discard rules we didn’t agree with. We needed to get the site out by working with oversight groups who, like a Roman emperor in a coliseum, could cause us major headaches with a thumbs-down. In our case, we got there in the end by doing the work to avoid the perception that we represented a major risk, but not at the cost of exploding our timeline. We were able to be both &lt;strong&gt;fast&lt;/strong&gt; (by comparison), and &lt;strong&gt;safe&lt;/strong&gt; (writing tests and documenting our approach).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-03-22-move-fast-stay-safe/#conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Conclusion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In traditional government culture, any change to the status quo is risky by definition. Ways of working that have largely been jettisoned in the private sector are still alive and well in government, although there is broad internal agreement that change is needed. As agile practitioners, the opportunity is clear: traditional government IT projects almost never stick to their budget or timeline, and often fail to deliver high-quality services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given how bad the status quo actually is, it seems like a no-brainer to switch to a widely successful model of project delivery that prioritizes quick feedback and early return-on-investment. Agile teams get more done with less overhead, largely because they are empowered to make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, agile teams in the government operate under pretty tough conditions, typically having to seek accommodation with an existing culture of extreme risk-avoidance. The strength of agile teams is their focus on shipping early and improving incrementally — but you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have to ship &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. Given this, it is extremely important to balance a commitment to safety with a desire to quickly get to a release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blending two contradictory approaches is never going to be easy, but it’s important to remain focused on delivering real value for citizens. Getting into debates with groups that are meeting-aholics or writing position papers arguing against paperwork-centric approaches means fighting on unfavourable terrain. To win this argument, you need to stop arguing: instead, prove your approach works by getting it to work. Pick a product, keep a tight rein on your scope, get it into the hands of users, and tell your story along the way. &lt;strong&gt;Moving fast&lt;/strong&gt; shows what is possible, while &lt;strong&gt;being safe&lt;/strong&gt; ensures you are viable.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Enterprise: the wrong bigger picture</title>
    <link href="https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/" />
    <updated>2022-01-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/</id>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;nav class=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#systems-a-working-definition&quot;&gt;Systems: a working definition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#what-does-this-have-to-do-with-government&quot;&gt;What does this have to do with government?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#the-enterprise-approach&quot;&gt;The Enterprise approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#single-disciplinary-teams&quot;&gt;Single-disciplinary teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#the-toll-road-to-enterprise-a-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;The toll road to enterprise: a thought experiment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#short-term-oversight-that-misses-the-point&quot;&gt;Short term: oversight that misses the point&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#long-term-oversight-as-bureaucratic-cement&quot;&gt;Long term: oversight as bureaucratic cement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#an-enterprise-exit-plan&quot;&gt;An enterprise exit plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#better-teams-multidisciplinary-instead-of-single-disciplinary&quot;&gt;Better teams: Multidisciplinary instead of single-disciplinary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#a-better-principle-user-needs-over-consistency&quot;&gt;A better principle: User needs over consistency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#better-systems-for-better-systemic-outcomes&quot;&gt;Better systems for better systemic outcomes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/nav&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Introduction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frequent visitors to my blog will know that essentially I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/&quot;&gt;one other post&lt;/a&gt; about how hard and slow it was making a small website in a federal department. Over the summer, I was &lt;s&gt;complaining about&lt;/s&gt; describing the compliance process to my sister and she was like, “Yeah Paul, it’s the government. If you don’t like paperwork, why do you work there?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, Julia, go for the jugular, why don’t you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a civil servant my whole working life — in Canada, in the UK, at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/westernusc&quot;&gt;Western U’s ‘student government’&lt;/a&gt; — and I’ve always had interesting stuff to work on and great colleagues. In fact, the public servants I know regularly go above and beyond — often overcoming awful processes and dated technology to get things done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let’s not get the wrong end of the stick here: it’s obvious to anyone with any sustained interaction with the Canadian government that our public service isn’t out here winning &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/govuk-wins-design-of-the-year-2013&quot;&gt;Design of the Year&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/free-automatic-tax-returns-benefits-1.5739678&quot;&gt;automatically filing our taxes&lt;/a&gt; (yet). More often we see stories about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/politics/article-ottawa-paid-out-400-million-in-phoenix-pay-compensation-to-federal/&quot;&gt;big, expensive IT failures&lt;/a&gt; and generalized anxiety about “&lt;a href=&quot;https://policyoptions.irpp.org/magazines/november-2021/speaking-tech-to-power/&quot;&gt;old mainframes and technology, some on the verge of collapse&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My sister’s perspective that ‘government is just inherently slow and paperwork-heavy’ isn’t what you would call deeply nuanced, but there’s definitely a link between her pessimism and a pattern of costly failures. So how do we square this circle: how is it that so many dedicated and well-meaning public servants working all over the government deliver so much crappy software?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we start seeing &lt;em&gt;patterns&lt;/em&gt; like this — similar outcomes from disparate departments — it’s a pretty sure sign that we are dealing with &lt;em&gt;systems&lt;/em&gt; rather than particular teams or individuals. A strong swimmer traveling against the current will always go slower and use more energy than an average swimmer (like me) swimming &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the current. When a system works against you, you spend more energy and get less done — eventually wearing down even the most talented folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s talk about systems: what they are, what they do, and how, sometimes, the problem isn’t when our systems stop working, it’s when they work too well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;systems-a-working-definition&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#systems-a-working-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Systems: a working definition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A system is a set of parts working together. Broadly speaking, systems are created when you need to do something more than once. Systems can be composed of physical parts (like a car), but for this post I will focus on systems as sequences of actions. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bonappetit.com/recipe/basically-spaghetti-pomodoro&quot;&gt;Basically Spaghetti Pomodoro&lt;/a&gt; is a sequence of actions resulting in, arguably, “THE best pomodoro sauce I’ve tasted at home.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good systems know what ‘good’ looks like and have the flexibility needed to improve over time. In the UK, anyone can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/apply-renew-passport&quot;&gt;apply for a new passport&lt;/a&gt; entirely online by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/photos-for-passports#how-to-get-a-digital-photo&quot;&gt;submitting a digital photo from their smartphone&lt;/a&gt;. In Canada, you need to bring in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/services/canadian-passports/photos.html&quot;&gt;physical regulation-sized photograph with a stamp and a ‘wet-ink’ signature on the back&lt;/a&gt;. Obviously, whoever designed the passport system several decades ago didn’t anticipate ubiquitous digital photography, but a good system adapts to a changing context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If good systems have clear priorities and are adaptable, bad systems are inflexible and confused about what is important. Even systems created with the best intentions degrade over time, so being able to cope with new situations is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-this-have-to-do-with-government&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#what-does-this-have-to-do-with-government&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;What does this have to do with government?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems have everything to do with government. I’ve defined a system as a set of parts working together to achieve a goal — in a broad sense, a government is the same thing. More narrowly, governments love a good recipe. Whether you call them ‘policies,’ ‘processes,’ ‘procedures,’ or ‘paperwork,’ (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/plan&quot;&gt;any other thesaurus.com alternative&lt;/a&gt;), government is stuffed with systematized ways of completing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes these heavily-routinized approaches get out of hand, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#internal-words&quot;&gt;when releasing a small website means writing a novel’s worth of paperwork&lt;/a&gt;. Governments are notorious for this kind of over-the-top bureaucratic process (known as ‘red-tape’).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While writing 36 thousand words is obviously too much for a simple website, this isn’t a post to make that argument. Instead, I want to talk about &lt;em&gt;why is it like this&lt;/em&gt;? How did we end up with processes that are okay with writing 36 thousand words?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems don’t always work that well, but they are always &lt;em&gt;supposed to&lt;/em&gt;. The processes we encounter — even if they seem illogical — were all deliberately introduced and there’s a reason they are still around. Usually there is an important principle they are meant to upload, it’s just a matter of finding it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the world of traditional government IT, there is one fundamental principle that almost no amount of usable software is worth trading for, and that principle is “&lt;strong&gt;enterprise&lt;/strong&gt;.” Investigating what it means to be ‘enterprise’ (and build ‘enterprise software’) helps us to better understand the processes we have, the teams created to enforce those processes, and how, ultimately, we get the outcomes we deserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-enterprise-approach&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#the-enterprise-approach&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Enterprise approach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian federal government, &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#uk-note&quot; id=&quot;uk-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;to a degree I never experienced in the UK&lt;/a&gt;, loves the word “enterprise”. &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2021/02/14/if-you-want-enterprise-services-to-be-good-make-them-optional/&quot;&gt;‘Enterprise’ is used both as a descriptor and an aspiration&lt;/a&gt;: it describes the kind of organization we are, but it is also an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/shared-services/ssc-3-enterprise-approach.html&quot;&gt;all-important principle to uphold&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before joining the Canadian public service, my understanding of “enterprise software” was something closer to ‘an ugly and hard-to-use backend system imposed on a captive workforce,’ but obviously this was just an uninformed impression and has no bearing on reality. Anyway, we’re here now, so let’s give it a fair shake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental idea behind ‘enterprise’ is ‘&lt;em&gt;consistency&lt;/em&gt;.’ If you are an ‘enterprise,’ it means you are a large organization with lots of teams and you want to make sure you are doing the same thing across those teams. Broadly understood, we could sum up the ‘enterprise’ mindset as: “if we have the same problem in different places, we should solve it the same way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea(l) is essentially positive and it appeals to an innate sense of fairness and objectivity most of us would agree with: that governments shouldn’t discriminate between people. For example, if I apply for a passport from Rivière-du-Loup, it wouldn’t be &lt;em&gt;fair&lt;/em&gt; for it to cost twice as much it would in Ottawa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the time, this focus on standards is useful. There are lots of things it makes sense to standardize on: team calendars, predictable email addresses, headers and footers that don’t change as you move between different sections of a larger site. The consistent look-and-feel shared by (most) departmental websites is a triumph of enterprise-centric thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moveover, it’s also &lt;em&gt;risky&lt;/em&gt; for government services to be inconsistent. Governments can be sued for failing to providing consistent outcomes — for example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/blind-woman-wins-case-against-federal-government-1.956042&quot;&gt;when government services aren’t accessible to different types of users&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, consistency can help both to simplify internal workflows and protect government departments from potential lawsuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But like with any high-minded principle, you can take ‘consistency’ too far — say writing a book’s worth of oversight documentation for a small site because it’s what you would do for a large site. While this level of oversight can seem absurd, it begins to make sense if we assume a core organizational principle of ‘consistency at any cost’ (sometimes literally, considering IT budgets for large projects &lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🙊&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But processes and principles are just words; organizations are made up of people. The outputs of any system depend on the people working within it, and we can learn a lot by looking at the makeup and incentives of internal teams. Specifically, enterprise-first environments tend to create silos of specialists that focus on internal oversight rather than external outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;single-disciplinary-teams&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#single-disciplinary-teams&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Single-disciplinary teams&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enterprise environments love creating &lt;em&gt;single-disciplinary teams&lt;/em&gt;: teams in which everyone has the same skill set (eg, a legal team of lawyers). &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#single-disiplinary-teams-note&quot; id=&quot;single-disiplinary-teams-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;Single-disciplinary teams&lt;/a&gt; are rooted in a desire to ensure consistency across a line of products. These teams are responsible for creating org-wide standards, and for &lt;em&gt;advising&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;approving&lt;/em&gt; products (but rarely for building them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On first blush, grouping people by role and giving them oversight across a range of products might not seem like too bad of an idea, but pretty quickly you start losing time and context as projects bounce around between these narrowly-focused teams. However, these are &lt;em&gt;emergent&lt;/em&gt; problems: they aren’t obvious at the outset but get worse as organizations grow. Let’s see how some of these dynamics play out by running through an imagined scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-toll-road-to-enterprise-a-thought-experiment&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#the-toll-road-to-enterprise-a-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The toll road to enterprise: a thought experiment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s imagine we run a small company. Let’s call ourselves EasyTax: we make a tax filing app for Canadians, and we have 6 employees in total: two developers, a designer, a marketer, a tax lawyer, and a founder who is responsible for product decisions. At this point, we have 1 product and 1 team. Each member contributes their specific expertise while also understanding the overall goal: building a great tax filing product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years later, our tax software is so popular that we have 5 different apps for different tax-filing scenarios: for individuals, for businesses, for students, for pet-owners, for government tech bloggers. Now there are 5 product teams, one for each app, and all with the same makeup as my original team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our 5 individual teams, we have 5 individual designers. But since each team works independently, variations emerge between products. When filing taxes, there are a large list of credits to sort through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One team keeps them all in a big list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another team uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/mobile-accordions/&quot;&gt;accordions&lt;/a&gt; to show or hide tax credits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A third team has a search box to look them up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though ‘showing tax credits’ is a common experience between all of my products, my designers are working independently and have implemented different solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the ‘enterprise’ model, this is no good. We don’t want each designer coming up with stuff on their own — now we have inconsistent outcomes. To rectify this, let’s create a centralized team made up only of designers. This new team will create ‘best-practice’ designs (eg, for showing tax credits) and then standardize it across products. This means individual product teams no longer have a dedicated designer, but instead we have a ‘design team’ responsible for reviewing and approving designs for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we imagine each of our products as a pie, we started with 5 pies and each pie had 1 designer assigned to it. Now, we have 1 consolidated design team responsible for a 10% slice of &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; pie — but only for how the pie looks, it doesn’t matter how it tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the design problem is solved, we want to do this with other roles too. Let’s create a legal team, a marketing team, and an architecture team. Instead of working on specific products from start to finish, each of these specialized teams is responsible for a slice of all products, so now all of our pies look like pie graphs (see figures below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
    &lt;summary&gt;Figure 1: Product teams with clear responsibility&lt;/summary&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
      &lt;img alt=&quot;Figure 1: Autonomous teams with clear responsibility&quot; src=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/img/articles/pies.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;3 autonomous product teams, each responsible for 1 product. Arrows represent responsibility for products. Responsibility is clear: there are 3 arrows, each product team is responsible for 1 product.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
    &lt;summary&gt;Figure 2: Advisory teams with complex responsibilities&lt;/summary&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
      &lt;img alt=&quot;Figure 2: Advisory teams with complex responsibilities&quot; src=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/img/articles/pies-2.png&quot; /&gt;
      &lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;3 product teams and 3 advisory teams, sharing responsibility for 3 products. Arrows represent responsibility for products. Responsibility is complex: there are 12 arrows, each product team is mostly responsible for 1 product, and each advisory team is partially responsible for every product.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time we create a new centralized oversight team, the actual team doing the work gets smaller, while the number of people “&lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2021/10/04/if-your-technology-leadership-is-more-into-blockchain-than-user-needs-youre-doomed/#leadership-density-or-leadership-signal-vs-noise&quot;&gt;involved in oversight, gate-keeping, and green-lighting&lt;/a&gt;” increases. The upshot of this process is that &lt;strong&gt;we are losing more time in meetings while reducing overall team capacity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all of our oversight teams ‘advising’ on every product, things start getting pretty confusing. (Imagine organizing an enterprise-style potluck where each person invited needs to provide 1 ingredient for every dish.) A lot of time is lost emailing to coordinate reviews and approvals for all our ongoing work. To address this, let’s come up with &lt;em&gt;a really clear and detailed plan&lt;/em&gt; that outlines exactly what everyone needs to do at every step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1HqtvTM7MksL6DpXXBxVut_6HuzGN-dH9KBtIlB5emAY/edit#slide=id.gf933083904_0_39&quot;&gt;Here is an example of what our really detailed and not-confusing plan might look like&lt;/a&gt;. (&lt;em&gt;psst, read the notes for the slide&lt;/em&gt;.) It’s a little hard to see in the diagram, but it visualizes an internal release pipeline that includes 93 discrete steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in this thought experiment, what started as a fairly intuitive team structure where everyone works together on a shared goal has turned into a highly choreographed performance where products ping-pong around between &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/honeygolightly/status/1225095639144550400&quot;&gt;teams that mostly watch, rather than do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In breaking up our product teams into siloed teams of specialists, we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have clearer standards in place although now everything takes longer. But is this actually a problem? Things &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; slower with all the extra meetings, but isn’t this preferable to an organization of uncoordinated, independent teams potentially overlooking the bigger picture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it turns out there is more than just one bigger picture. There is a short-term and a long-term cost to this kind of org structure. In the short term, teams narrowly-focused on a single domain can end up missing the forest for the wrong forest. And in the long term, an over-emphasis on following standards can easily lead to internal stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;short-term-oversight-that-misses-the-point&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#short-term-oversight-that-misses-the-point&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Short term: oversight that misses the point&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I was on a team building a user recruitment site. After putting together some early designs and beginning work on the first few pages, we reached out to the oversight teams we needed approval from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group advising on data security looked over our designs and frowned at the signup form. They strongly advised us to remove the ‘email’ field. If we did that, they said, it would be easier to approve our project because not collecting personal data is better for data security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;the whole point of our site&lt;/em&gt; was to collect the emails of interested users, we rebutted. How would we follow up with people if we had no way to contact them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Well, I am just telling you, it will be harder to get it approved this way,’ was the response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well-meaning advice, to be sure, but it completely overlooked our team’s goal. It didn’t make sense to build a user recruitment website that couldn’t actually recruit users. From our perspective, this group didn’t understand the bigger picture of what our site was for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, from the data team’s perspective, &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; were the ones missing the big picture. Their responsibility was data security writ large, and data you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; collect can never be hacked or leaked. Their standard recommendation — ‘don’t collect emails’ — was consistent with their goal of reducing personal data collection across the organization. So there was actually &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; bigger picture here, it was just the wrong bigger picture for our site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little websites”&lt;br /&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/a_foolish_consistency_is_the_hobgoblin_of_little_minds&quot;&gt;Ralph Waldo Emerson&lt;/a&gt;, replying-all after our meeting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the surrealism of that discussion, we ultimately kept the email field and went on to launch the site. Even though we spent some time in unproductive meetings, we still got our way in the end. Problem solved, right? Well, maybe in the short-term, but in the long-tem, this ‘enterprise’ preference for rigid standards over flexible implementation can result in a stagnant organizational culture incapable of incorporating new tools or ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-term-oversight-as-bureaucratic-cement&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#long-term-oversight-as-bureaucratic-cement&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Long term: oversight as bureaucratic cement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an enterprise organization, local variations are heavily discouraged. They aren’t impossible, but they’re certainly not easy. Under normal circumstances, you shouldn’t do things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install applications that aren’t pre-approved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add new technology to your tech stack that hasn’t been vetted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use designs that aren’t standard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sign up for new services other teams aren’t using&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#the-content-management-system-an-example&quot;&gt;my previous article&lt;/a&gt;, I outlined how a ‘maximum risk’ interpretation of adding a CMS to our website resulted in excessive documentation. On this same team, we burned a lot of time and energy requesting an online task-tracking app (a bit like a team todo-list: you use it to keep track of who is working on what). The reason it became such a sticking point was that a different task-tracking app was internally pre-approved for all teams to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take the ‘enterprise’ perspective: there was already a standard solution in place and our team was being troublesome in trying to contravene it. If this application really was that much better, why didn’t we use &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#new-software-note&quot; id=&quot;new-software-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;the “request new software” process&lt;/a&gt; and submit it as the new standard for all teams to use? Why should we be different, picking our own thing that nobody else was using? Moreover, everyone knows it’s cheaper to ‘buy in bulk’ rather than spending small amounts for one team at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took us about 6 months of intermittent meetings, written justifications, trial accounts, etc, before it was finally approved for our use. ‘Buying in bulk’ to save money is a good theory, but it doesn’t consider the loss of productivity from teams finding workarounds for clunky tools — not to mention the cost of these long-running discussions. We likely spent more money in employee salaries to attend meetings and write documentation than if we had been allowed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2021/07/11/paying-for-low-cost-cloud-services-on-a-departmental-credit-card/&quot;&gt;make a low-cost purchase on a credit card&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my past job at the UK government, we would have made our decision in the morning and had it set up by the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the short/medium term, problems like these can often be resolved. However, the pernicious long-term effect is one where it costs so much time and energy to introduce new ideas or processes that eventually your whole tech stack (and maybe &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gc.ca/eng/index.html&quot;&gt;your homepage&lt;/a&gt;) looks like it came out of a time capsule. The ‘enterprise’ preference for layering on oversight and approvals is essentially a kind of bureaucratic cement that slows down your organizational agility over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Without an easy way for teams to try out new technologies, new software, and new designs, you wind up stifling your long-term ability to incrementally modernize.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s true that consistency is important, but, taken to an extreme, it can lead to a situation where teams are structurally unable to introduce new ideas. Once that happens, you end up relying on massively expensive, hugely disruptive ‘transformation/modernization’ megaprojects, which try to introduce a raft of new technologies and process changes all at once. In other words, &lt;a href=&quot;https://large-government-of-canada-it-projects.github.io/#are-large-it-projects-likely-to-be-successful&quot;&gt;exactly the kind of large IT projects that fail most often&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-enterprise-exit-plan&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#an-enterprise-exit-plan&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;An enterprise exit plan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully by this point you’re open to the idea that ‘enterprise’ is Not That Chill. Consistent look and feel and standardized outcomes are important principles, but not when it means multiplying all your timelines by a factor of 10 and losing internal cohesion to information silos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as Billy McFarland famously said “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rollingstone.com/culture/culture-features/fyre-festival-billy-mcfarland-cult-positivity-optimism-783443/&quot;&gt;We’re not a problems-focused group, we’re a solutions-oriented group, we need to have a positive attitude about this&lt;/a&gt;.” It’s all well and good to burn down 50 years’ worth of organizational theory in a blog post, but what are my solutions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a fairly long post already, so I will be (relatively) brief — but I plan to expand on these themes in future posts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#bd-email&quot;&gt;sign up&lt;/a&gt;! It will be a hoot! &lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🦉&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post has focused on two problematic aspects of ‘enterprise’ culture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘Consistency’ as &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; all-important principle to uphold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single-disciplinary teams that approve products but don‘t build them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s address them in reverse order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;better-teams-multidisciplinary-instead-of-single-disciplinary&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#better-teams-multidisciplinary-instead-of-single-disciplinary&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Better teams: Multidisciplinary instead of single-disciplinary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Enterprise’ organizations rely on single-disciplinary teams where everyone has &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; skill but works across &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; products. If we compare this way of working to how teams are organized in modern software companies (or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ontario.ca/page/digital-service-standard#section-3&quot;&gt;modern teams in other governments&lt;/a&gt;) we see exactly the opposite approach being implemented successfully. Multi-disciplinary teams work on &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; product and include &lt;em&gt;all the skills needed&lt;/em&gt; to build and operate a working service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, these teams must have authority over their products. Multidisciplinary teams working in an oversight-centric ‘enterprise’ environment &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; able to design and build their own products to some degree, but team decisions can always be vetoed by groups with approval authority. Creating multidisciplinary teams is a good start, but their effectiveness will be limited if they can still be overruled later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we rewind to the start of our EasyTax thought experiment, this is exactly the kind of team we started with. Small, multidisciplinary product teams chat with each other instead of booking meetings, and all team members understand the overall goal they are trying to achieve. By keeping teams nimble and reducing organizational gatekeeping, we end up with teams that are more effective: taking less time to deliver services that users prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-better-principle-user-needs-over-consistency&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#a-better-principle-user-needs-over-consistency&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;A better principle: User needs over consistency&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an enterprise organization, ‘consistency’ isn’t just a ‘nice-to-have’, it’s the central assumption from which everything flows. The standards-centric mindset of the enterprise approach is a really clear principle: it helps us structure teams, put together policies, and suggests how to approach decisions. To quote Archimedes, “Give me but one firm spot on which to stand and I will move the earth.” If we scrap ‘consistency,’ where do we stand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is ‘user needs’. User needs is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles#start-with-user-needs&quot;&gt;#1 design principle in the UK government&lt;/a&gt;, and incidentally, it’s also at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/digital-government/government-canada-digital-standards.html#ds1&quot;&gt;the top of the Government of Canada’s Digital Playbook&lt;/a&gt;. Whenever you find yourself at a crossroads, ask ‘What is best from a user’s perspective?’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s think about applying for a passport in Canada: would it be better to allow digital uploads or to stick with physical photos? Taking a departmental perspective, physical photos are harder to fabricate and we currently have the resources and expertise to manage them. But let’s reframe this from the end user’s perspective: What will make this service the easiest to use for the most people? If we asked 10 people at the mall right now, what would they tell us? Undoubtedly, we will find that digital uploads are preferred by people applying for passports in Canada today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example of the user recruitment site I worked on is revealing here too. You can understand why the data security team would suggest removing the email field from the signup form, but no user would ask for that change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘User needs’ corrects for a serious bias in our org design. &lt;strong&gt;Of all the internal teams we have to meet with to triple-check and approve all of our decisions, the actual users of the service are almost never present in these negotiations.&lt;/strong&gt; You can get approved by &lt;em&gt;every group&lt;/em&gt; you have to meet with, and &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; end up releasing a site that doesn’t work for its intended audience. This is how you end up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://digital.hbs.edu/platform-rctom/submission/the-failed-launch-of-www-healthcare-gov/&quot;&gt;problematic launches like the original healthcare.gov&lt;/a&gt;, where, despite the huge number of people involved (and an eye watering amount of cash), it failed as soon as real people tried using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;better-systems-for-better-systemic-outcomes&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2022-01-24-enterprise-the-wrong-bigger-picture/#better-systems-for-better-systemic-outcomes&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Better systems for better systemic outcomes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping an eye on the big picture is important, but we have multiple bigger pictures to choose from. The best bigger picture is the one that puts end users first — it’s the most likely to lead to services that are clear and easy to use. Under an ‘enterprise-first’ organization, many of the procedures set up are internally-focused, with compliance teams asking themselves ‘What is best for this department?’ We need to transition to processes that look outwards, asking what is best for Canadians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The systems we encounter at work are not inevitable or eternal. They are designed and implemented by human beings, and when they work properly, they help us get things done more easily than if we didn’t have them. Good systems are useful, adaptable, and consistently deliver good outcomes. Once a system is none of these things, it’s time to change.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Paperweight: a cautionary tale of onerous oversight</title>
    <link href="https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/" />
    <updated>2021-12-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/</id>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;nav class=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#why-is-it-so-hard&quot;&gt;Why is it so hard?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#old-approaches-to-new-ideas&quot;&gt;Old approaches to new ideas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#talking-about-what-we-do&quot;&gt;Talking about what we do&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#spreading-the-message&quot;&gt;Spreading the message&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#summing-up&quot;&gt;Summing up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#our-site-in-numbers&quot;&gt;Our site, in numbers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#coding-in-the-open&quot;&gt;Coding in the open&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#measuring-the-hard-to-measure&quot;&gt;Measuring the hard to measure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#internal-words&quot;&gt;Internal words&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#how-many-words-is-a-lot-of-words&quot;&gt;How many words is a lot of words?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#public-words&quot;&gt;Public words&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#how-did-we-get-here&quot;&gt;How did we get here?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#the-content-management-system-an-example&quot;&gt;The Content Management System: an example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#the-way-forward-when-less-is-better&quot;&gt;The way forward: when less is better&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/nav&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Introduction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 31st, in the year of our Lord 2021, my team, working in a federal department, launched &lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/home&quot;&gt;a new website for citizen engagement&lt;/a&gt;. By showcasing early versions of ongoing projects and inviting Canadians to give feedback, our “Labs” site prioritizes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/digital-government/government-canada-digital-standards.html#ds3&quot;&gt;transparency&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/digital-government/government-canada-digital-standards.html#ds1&quot;&gt;accountability to citizens&lt;/a&gt; — important ideals that traditional government projects don’t always live up to. Despite the implied Grand Ideals™ however, it’s a relatively simple site: the equivalent of putting a small blog online. To a casual visitor, it has 4 pages and it does 2 things: you can see &lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/projects&quot;&gt;a list of upcoming new services&lt;/a&gt;, and you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/signup&quot;&gt;volunteer to test them out&lt;/a&gt;. In large part due to its inherent simplicity, our small but determined team was able to launch it on time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did it feel good to finally release it? Heck yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was it easy to get there? F*ck no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-it-so-hard&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#why-is-it-so-hard&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Why is it so hard?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/11/13/magazine/design-issue-code-for-america.html&quot;&gt;Why is it so hard to make a website for the government?&lt;/a&gt;” asks a twirling ASCII banana in a 2016 New York Magazine feature — something many of us have surely wondered. Well, this is the kind of deceptively simple question that probably merits a working group or at least 3 committees with overlapping acronyms. But since I don’t have 3 years to not come up with an answer, let’s see if we can glean any wisdom from my experience building and releasing a small cloud-hosted site in a large federal department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-approaches-to-new-ideas&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#old-approaches-to-new-ideas&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Old approaches to new ideas&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a decade ago, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/government-digital-service/about&quot;&gt;Government Digital Service&lt;/a&gt; in the UK spearheaded a new style of online service delivery characterized by smaller, autonomous teams making quick, iterative releases and &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#open-by-default&quot;&gt;openly talking about their work&lt;/a&gt;. Rather than burning heaps of time writing ‘make-work’ documents for internal committees, digital product teams in the UK (and I worked on several) focus on quickly building services and then testing them with actual citizens. It was found to be a successful model — leading to cheaper, faster, and better quality online services — and they haven’t looked back since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Government of Canada has not yet undergone a large-scale transition in this direction, although there are some attempts being made (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/diseases/coronavirus-disease-covid-19/covid-alert.html&quot;&gt;COVID Alert&lt;/a&gt;, for example, was &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/10/30/working-in-the-open-firsts-for-covid-alert/&quot;&gt;built quickly and in the open&lt;/a&gt;). More commonly, however, Canadian federal government IT projects can easily spend months or years and (tens of) millions of dollars in “planning phases” before any part of the service is actually ready to be used by actual Canadian citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional IT government projects try to guard against the possibility of costly mistakes by requiring product teams to seek approvals from a revolving door of committees and groups. Unfortunately, the accumulated time and energy spent appeasing these various gatekeepers can be just as costly to the team as the mistakes they are trying to prevent. In our case, our 12-page website needed approval from around 8 different groups over a 6-month period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the alternative team-based model widely used in the UK, &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#users-note&quot; id=&quot;users-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;the possibility of costly mistakes is mitigated by actively reaching out to and testing the service with its eventual users&lt;/a&gt;. By focusing on getting feedback early and often from end users, mistaken assumptions are corrected early in the process by those whose opinions will ultimately matter the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our “Labs” site, intended to facilitate exactly this kind of citizen engagement and testing, is a small but important step in creating a more responsive, more accountable government. Unfortunately, actually launching it meant slogging through a morass of meetings and meddlers. It’s all well and good to champion tomorrow’s leaner and faster ways of working, but in our present context, we were firmly trapped in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;talking-about-what-we-do&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#talking-about-what-we-do&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Talking about what we do&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#closed-by-default&quot;&gt;The federal government tends to be pretty buttoned up&lt;/a&gt; about what it’s working on and how things are going. Sometimes this is justified: state secrets, upcoming changes to the tax code, military evacuations — there are definitely things that need to be closely guarded lest they put people in danger or let people game the system. Building a small website to ask Canadians for feedback on prototypes is absolutely &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; something that belongs in that category. Rather, my experience reveals something common across government: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2021/01/12/onerous-levels-of-oversight/&quot;&gt;onerous levels of oversight&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in our case, it often happens that the compliance activities demand more time and energy than actually delivering the outcome. But how can we attempt to measure this, and what are the factors that lead to this outcome? Well, I’m glad you asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;spreading-the-message&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#spreading-the-message&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Spreading the message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kernel of this post is a presentation I gave a week after launch. Our core product team was deliberately small enough to get things done without getting in each other’s way, but this means you have to talk about what you do if you want people to hear about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This is a good thing, by the way. Small teams getting on with their work and giving demos is far better than large teams where everyone knows nothing is going on.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a small, multidisciplinary team meant we could quickly build the site itself, but it also resulted in our nearly getting snowed under as we progressed through the various internal gatekeepers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My sense was that most of our compliance activities were based on inertia rather than utility, and I didn’t believe it was widely understood how much was being asked of us. So after the launch I put some numbers together to at least partially answer the question: “Why is it so hard to make a website for the government?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So! With no further ado, this is a numbers-centric look at what it took to launch our “Labs” site inside a large federal department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;summing-up&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#summing-up&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Summing up&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To recap, we launched a user engagement site for the teams working on the next iteration of the department’s user portal. The site hosts &lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/projects&quot;&gt;a public listing of prototypes&lt;/a&gt; — ‘sneak previews’ of new services being worked on. You can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/signup&quot;&gt;sign up to be a ‘user research participant’&lt;/a&gt; and give feedback on early versions of new services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s it: it’s a list of prototypes and a signup form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let’s be more data-y about this — by which I mean, &lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#numbers-note&quot; id=&quot;numbers-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;let’s use numbers to tell a story&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-site-in-numbers&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#our-site-in-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Our site, in numbers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some basic numbers that give a sense of what we’re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;12&lt;/code&gt; pages
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;4&lt;/code&gt; pages most visitors will see
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/home&quot;&gt;Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/about&quot;&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/projects&quot;&gt;Projects&lt;/a&gt; (the ‘catalogue’)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alpha.service.canada.ca/signup&quot;&gt;Sign up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;4&lt;/code&gt; prototypes of upcoming services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that the site is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/digital-government/government-canada-digital-standards.html#ds2&quot;&gt;frequently being iterated on&lt;/a&gt;, so if it doesn’t look exactly like that by the time you’re reading this, that’s okay — it’s supposed to change over time. Luckily, we can also follow along on GitHub, where &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DTS-STN/Alpha-Site&quot;&gt;the source code is publicly available for anyone to see&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;coding-in-the-open&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#coding-in-the-open&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Coding in the open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it seems kind of nerdy, but public source code is really valuable for government teams to release. As citizens, we typically only see final versions of things — online services, ad campaigns, reports, and so on. We get the finished product, but we don’t see how it came to be. By looking at the public source code, we get a lot of visibility into the progress of the team, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DTS-STN/Alpha-Site/commits/main?after=e2b07245c7a744e63a86edc0e598257018a1d38e+440&amp;amp;branch=main&quot;&gt;When it was first started&lt;/a&gt;: March 17&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DTS-STN/Alpha-Site/commits/main&quot;&gt;When the last change was&lt;/a&gt;: Yesterday (as of December 15, 2021)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DTS-STN/Alpha-Site/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;How many people have worked on it&lt;/a&gt;: 15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DTS-STN/Alpha-Site/graphs/commit-activity&quot;&gt;If the team works on Sundays&lt;/a&gt;: Only once (week of June 11)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Canada’s federal Digital Standards call for “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/digital-government/government-canada-digital-standards.html#ds3&quot;&gt;work[ing] in the open by default&lt;/a&gt;,” this is exactly what they are referring to. By making source code publicly available, we can get really good insights into the technical portion of the product. However, this is only half the story: there is also a submerged body of governance and compliance work that is much harder to quantify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;measuring-the-hard-to-measure&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#measuring-the-hard-to-measure&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Measuring the hard to measure&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we talk about ‘data’, we’re usually talking about things that are easy to count and measure, but — as the cast of Rent knows — how do you measure a year(ly release)? (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XNbwiGbETSQ&quot;&gt;In midnights? In cups of coffee?&lt;/a&gt;) Activities that don’t leave behind structured data can be pretty hard to quantify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our website, it would be really interesting to measure things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many meetings were scheduled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many emails were sent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total number of people involved outside of the core team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, given the crush of meetings and emails that myself and many of my colleagues had on a daily basis, reliably collecting this data isn’t really practical. My colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sboots&quot;&gt;Sean Boots&lt;/a&gt; built a &lt;a href=&quot;https://meetingcostcalculator.ca/&quot;&gt;Meeting Cost Calculator&lt;/a&gt;, but the underlying data we would need to plug into it isn’t available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; we measure related to project governance? Well, let’s look at some artifacts we &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; have: project documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;internal-words&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#internal-words&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Internal words&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the team, we used a shared folder for all the documents and diagrams created in the process of launching the site. All together, we have 45 documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But “45 documents” on its own doesn’t tell us much. What we want to know is how much effort they represent: what’s actually &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; these documents? In other words, how much relevant, original text did real people (including me) have to write to get this site over the line?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To try and quantify this, I opened every document (ignoring duplicates and diagrams), selected all the original text (removing templated content), pasted all of it into a new doc, and did a quick word count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🥁&lt;/span&gt; Drumroll please… &lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🥁&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;39 230&lt;/code&gt; (!) words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you add up all the original (&lt;em&gt;non copy+pasted&lt;/em&gt;) text in our various documents, presentations, justifications, and rationales, we get 39,230 words, which — to me — sounds like a lot of words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-many-words-is-a-lot-of-words&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#how-many-words-is-a-lot-of-words&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;How many words is a lot of words?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;is it&lt;/em&gt; a lot of words? Of course, thirty-nine thousand and change sounds like a lot but what can we compare this to?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went looking for comparisons and I found a listing of &lt;a href=&quot;http://commonplacebook.com/art/books/word-count-for-famous-novels/&quot;&gt;word counts for famous novels&lt;/a&gt;. If we pull out a couple, this is where we sit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;36 363&lt;/code&gt; words: &lt;em&gt;The Lion, the Witch, and the Wardrobe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;39 230&lt;/code&gt; words: compliance documentation for our 12-page website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;47 094&lt;/code&gt; words: &lt;em&gt;The Great Gatsby&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we are in good company here, sandwiched between a beloved children’s novel and a classic tale of superficial excess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, November (so recently past) is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://nanowrimo.org/&quot;&gt;National Novel Writing Month&lt;/a&gt;”: the goal of which is to write a 50k word novel, something we were only a few documents short of achieving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And none of this is user-facing, mind you. Those 39,230 words represent only &lt;em&gt;the tax&lt;/em&gt; we paid to move our project through all the various internal groups and committees. Since none of that work is available to the public, even if we were writing the next Great Canadian Federal Novel (we weren’t), you would never get to see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;public-words&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#public-words&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Public words&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about the words that &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; user-facing? I’ve said a few times that it’s a small website, so maybe I should qualify that. I’ve counted nearly 40k words of internal documentation, but what is the word count of the actual site itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned earlier, there are 12 individual pages, if you know where to find them — and since I was on the team, I did know where to find them. Pretty basic methodology again here: select all the text on the screen, paste into a large document, and grab a word count once you finish with all the pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;4 305&lt;/code&gt; words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, 4,305 words is nothing to sneeze at, but it’s hardly going to be accepted as &lt;a href=&quot;https://nanowrimo.org/sign-up&quot;&gt;our NaNoWriMo submission&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, if we do a bit of math, we get this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;39,230 / 4,305 = 9.11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rounding down, we’re looking at roughly a 9:1 ratio of internal vs. external content. To put that another way, &lt;strong&gt;for every 10 words we write on this team, 1 word is for the site itself — the actual thing we are trying to release — and 9 words are for internal governance&lt;/strong&gt;, to be read once or twice (if ever), and then filed away somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case, it meant that for our 12-page site, we ended up writing almost as much as the Great Gatsby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Never was so much written by so few for no reason.”&lt;br /&gt;
— Winston Churchill once said, referring to our website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-we-get-here&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#how-did-we-get-here&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;How did we get here?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’ve written a lot about the &lt;em&gt;volume&lt;/em&gt; of documentation, but I haven’t touched on the content itself. We were building a small site which, at launch, was assessed having &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; sensitive data — in theory this should mitigate potential security and privacy concerns. Given that, how was it that we ended up writing so much for such a small deliverable? For me, the answer stems from systemic assumptions — what you might call an ‘organizational common sense’ — around managing risk, which, over time, have created a culture of amateur novel writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-content-management-system-an-example&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#the-content-management-system-an-example&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Content Management System: an example&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our team, we had several developers and two content writers. When a content writer wanted to change some text on the site, they would email those changes to developers, who would update the code. Emailing updates like this can introduce tension into the team. The person sending the change wants to see it quickly, which means interrupting the developer from whatever they were working on. The more often this happens, the more guilty the content writer feels and the more annoyed the developer gets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling content writers to edit the content directly relieves this tension: by using a Content Management System (CMS), a content writer can log in, update the text, and press “Publish”. Now developers can work on other tasks and content writers can make changes whenever they want. But there is a tradeoff here: setting up and maintaining a CMS creates work for developers. If the content doesn’t change that often, maybe sending emails is good enough. Ultimately, it comes down to team preference. Does it save us time? Is this how we want to work together? What if we try it out? If it works, let’s keep using it. If it doesn’t work, let’s get rid of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our team eventually decided to add a CMS, so we picked one that worked for us and set it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a bunch of (valid) questions that arise when adding a CMS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who gets an account?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What permissions does each account have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the password rules like?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the vetting process for allowing new users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the onboarding process for new users?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the decommissioning process for accounts that are no longer needed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why don’t the accounts integrate with Outlook accounts people already have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has administrator privileges to the infrastructure?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the plan if it stops working?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What other CMSes did you look at?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was your analyses of the other CMSes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the kinds of questions internal compliance teams will ask (and many more!). But is it worth asking them all in our case? Let’s imagine two opposing opinions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opinion 1&lt;/strong&gt;: These are all important and necessary questions to have answered before a site can be released, &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; in a government context where we have to consider any possible security implications and/or a loss of reputation. This CMS is new to the organization. All new technology requires need comprehensive documentation around how it works, how it will be used, by whom, and how it will be supported in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opinion 2&lt;/strong&gt;: The team has found something that improves their workflow and it is only being used by the 5 people on the team. The site is assessed as &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; having sensitive data and the ‘reputational risk’ of an occasional typo isn’t that serious. Yes, it’s a new CMS but it only affects this one team, and they don’t even know if they want to keep using this 6 months down the road. Let’s skip the documentation for now and see how it goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of middle ground in the space between each of these perspectives, but, in practice, we ended up very close to Opinion 1. While there is an important principle represented by the “comprehensive documentation” opinion, there is almost no consideration given to the context of the project. The CMS &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; a new technology, so that represented a risk. However, there were significant mitigating factors. It didn’t impact any other teams, it didn’t have any sensitive data, and there were only 5 accounts — all for people we worked with directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zooming out a bit, our team identified a way to improve how we work together, spent a couple days putting together a potential solution, and that could have been it: let’s see how it goes and re-evaluate in a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, a culture of ‘everything new must be comprehensively documented upfront, no exceptions’ meant putting together huge amounts of documentation (maybe 6-7 thousand words of), all before getting the practical experience to know for sure if this CMS was something we wanted to stick with long-term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ‘organizational common-sense’ operating here is that &lt;strong&gt;more&lt;/strong&gt; documentation equals &lt;strong&gt;less&lt;/strong&gt; risk. If some problem occurs in the future, you can refer to documentation which (hopefully &lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🤞&lt;/span&gt;) describes how that problem should be handled. Therefore, any time we introduce a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; technology or a trial &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; way of doing things — anything we can’t copy and paste from a previous document — it is &lt;em&gt;really important&lt;/em&gt; that it is heavily documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the unaccounted-for long-term risk is one where high-effort processes suffocate grassroots learning and experimentation, leading to organizational stagnation. Our team was looking to save ~45 minutes a week, so we picked up a new technology as a potential remediation. Unwittingly, this meant signing up for ~40-60 hours of documenting, diagraming, presenting, justifying, etc — far outweighing the potential benefit of the CMS. Something that was meant to optimize the team’s workflow and relieve a mild inefficiency turned into a black hole of effort: consuming hours and hours of time for documentation that few people will ever read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the cost of trialling new things is so punishing, it is not practical or even rational to try. Eventually, you end up in a situation where “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/federal-it-systems-critical-failure-1.5448871&quot;&gt;aging government computer systems [...] are pushing 60 years old and built on ‘outdated technology’ that can no longer be maintained&lt;/a&gt;,” as reported by the CBC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-way-forward-when-less-is-better&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-15-paperweight/#the-way-forward-when-less-is-better&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The way forward: when less is better&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the department, the expectation for new technology and new approaches was understood to be about &lt;em&gt;speeding up&lt;/em&gt; development cycles in the service of better meeting the needs of &lt;em&gt;end users&lt;/em&gt;. However, accompanying changes to internal compliance were &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/01/28/introducing-agile-to-large-organizations-is-a-subtractive-process-not-an-additive-one/&quot;&gt;a purely additive process&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;em&gt;slowed down&lt;/em&gt; the team with excessive paperwork, resulting in a much greater focus on &lt;em&gt;internal gatekeepers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of adopting an attitude of ‘let’s see what makes sense for this application,’ it was treated more like ‘let’s do everything we currently do, plus extra documentation now that we’re adding new technology.’ Rather than adding ever more checks and imbalances to procedures created decades ago, we need to engage with the question of whether burying teams under reams of paper results in &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; measurably better outcomes for Canadians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I’m not saying we shouldn’t have &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; compliance processes — of course we need security reviews and internal documentation of some kind. But above all we need procedures that are &lt;em&gt;proportional&lt;/em&gt; to the outcomes, that &lt;em&gt;adapt&lt;/em&gt; to changing situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But isn’t excessive paperwork just ‘how government works?’”, I hear you asking. Well, ‘how government works’ changes over time. Small, nimble teams with more autonomy and dramatically less overhead have become a norm in the UK, where they have an even larger government than ours. In my previous life as a UK civil servant, if I had wanted to introduce a CMS to a small site with no sensitive data, I would have needed buy-in from my team and to write maybe 1 page of explanation. There’s no reason we can’t take the same approach here in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hoping for different outcomes without reducing the overhead of internal procedures will only get us so far. Currently, many government teams spend an inordinate proportion of effort managing internal stakeholders instead of focusing on external users. We need to &lt;strong&gt;create space for teams to use their judgement&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;lower the cost of experimentation&lt;/strong&gt; if we are to realize the ideal of a truly responsive, citizen-centric government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, we can’t build the services of the future without letting go of the assumptions of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Introducing Federal Field Notes</title>
    <link href="https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/" />
    <updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/</id>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;nav class=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#obligatory-disclaimer&quot;&gt;Obligatory Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#the-pitch&quot;&gt;The pitch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#why-should-i-listen-to-you&quot;&gt;Why should I listen to you?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#open-by-default&quot;&gt;Open by default&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#closed-by-default&quot;&gt;Closed by default&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#make-things-open&quot;&gt;Make things open&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#whats-the-angle&quot;&gt;What’s the angle?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#the-whole-story&quot;&gt;The whole story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/nav&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;obligatory-disclaimer&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#obligatory-disclaimer&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Obligatory Disclaimer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should go without saying, but just to be totally explicit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The views and opinions expressed here are credited to individual authors (currently: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pcraig3&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;) and don’t reflect the views of teammates or employers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-pitch&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#the-pitch&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The pitch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal Field Notes is a newsletter about digital transformation in the federal Government of Canada (GoC), written from first-hand experience. It catalogues the ups and downs of working to create a more responsive, empathetic, and user-centred public service. &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#bd-email&quot;&gt;Tune in&lt;/a&gt; for interesting stories, useful observations, and practical advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-should-i-listen-to-you&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#why-should-i-listen-to-you&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Why should I listen to you?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fair question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked in government for the better part of a decade now: I was ~3 years at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gds.blog.gov.uk/about/&quot;&gt;Government Digital Service (GDS)&lt;/a&gt; in the UK, and I’ve been nearly 4 years in Canada, mostly at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://digital.canada.ca/&quot;&gt;Canadian Digital Service (CDS)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;open-by-default&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#open-by-default&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Open by default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At GDS, I spent the majority of my time working as a Developer on the (&lt;a class=&quot;Footnotes__ref&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#digital-marketplace-note&quot; id=&quot;digital-marketplace-ref&quot; aria-describedby=&quot;footnotes-label&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;UK’s&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalmarketplace.service.gov.uk/&quot;&gt;Digital Marketplace&lt;/a&gt;, but also &lt;a href=&quot;https://gds.blog.gov.uk/tag/performance-platform/&quot;&gt;the (erstwhile) Performance Platform&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;abbr title=&quot;Rest in Peace&quot;&gt;RIP&lt;/abbr&gt;), and, very briefly, on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notifications.service.gov.uk/&quot;&gt;GOV.UK Notify&lt;/a&gt;. As a civil servant for the UK government, I was always on design-led multidisciplinary teams with autonomy over their technical stack and product decisions. We used modern technology, regularly tested upcoming features with users, set up continuous integration for daily releases, and put nearly all of our work on into &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/alphagov&quot;&gt;public Github repositories&lt;/a&gt;. In sum, we were following &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/government/system/digital-government/government-canada-digital-standards.html&quot;&gt;the Government of Canada’s Digital Standards Playbook&lt;/a&gt; to the letter. &lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;😉&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving back to Canada in 2018, I was surprised to learn how closed-off our government culture is by contrast, where many (most?) federal public servants don’t have an easy way to publicly share the work they do everyday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;closed-by-default&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#closed-by-default&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Closed by default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve experienced, traditional Canadian government culture is fairly opaque, mostly due to over-calibrated assumptions around risk: eg, that teams communicating openly with the public may cause public embarrassment or leak details of upcoming work that they aren’t supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What if this ends up in the Globe?” is a sentiment heard quite a few times, implying that media stories that aren’t carefully managed are necessarily bad news. Compare this to GDS in the UK, whose early successes resulted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/government-computing-network/2012/jul/25/cabinet-office-transactional-services-data-gds&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2012/nov/06/government-services-digital-default-save&quot;&gt;positive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2013/nov/15/government-digital-service-best-startup-europe-invest&quot;&gt;media&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/public-leaders-network/2014/sep/08/local-government-digital-service-gds&quot;&gt;mentions&lt;/a&gt;, or COVID Alert, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.michaelgeist.ca/2020/08/why-i-installed-the-covid-alert-app&quot;&gt;specifically&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalnews.ca/news/7263448/coronavirus-covid-19-tracing-app-canada-how-it-works/&quot;&gt;lauded&lt;/a&gt; for its &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/10/30/working-in-the-open-firsts-for-covid-alert/&quot;&gt;openness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A culture of silence is bad for all of us: for public servants who can’t (or don’t &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; they can) easily share the interesting work they do, and for the public, who often distrust what they perceive as a large, inscrutable organization, unable to see the many motivated and passionate individuals working on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;make-things-open&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#make-things-open&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Make things open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The UK’s highly successful government digital transformation was predicated on &lt;a href=&quot;https://gds.blog.gov.uk/2014/07/22/making-things-open-making-things-better/&quot;&gt;a culture of transparency&lt;/a&gt;: working in the open, blogging frequently, encouraging public involvement/discussion, and a strong commitment to plain language. (Check out GDS’ “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/style-guide/a-to-z-of-gov-uk-style#words-to-avoid&quot;&gt;Words to avoid&lt;/a&gt;” in their plain-language guide — see how many you come across regularly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of this, the UK team working on a new government identity platform &lt;a href=&quot;https://gds.blog.gov.uk/category/id-assurance/&quot;&gt;is blogging openly about their progress&lt;/a&gt;, even &lt;a href=&quot;https://gds.blog.gov.uk/2021/12/01/one-login-for-government-december-2021-update/&quot;&gt;talking to an impressive 720 &lt;em&gt;end users&lt;/em&gt; in 7 months&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal Field Notes continues this all-important tradition of government transparency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-angle&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#whats-the-angle&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;What’s the angle?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’m aiming to do here is open up a place to talk about digital government in Canada in a way that’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/03/03/find-the-truth-tell-the-truth/&quot;&gt;honest&lt;/a&gt;, insightful, and a little irreverent. Government IT transformation is hard, but it doesn’t have to be boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-whole-story&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-12-introducing-federal-field-notes/#the-whole-story&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;The whole story&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find a lot of public discussions about digital transformation in the GoC are couched in a kind of relentless positivity — obviously it’s great to trumpet your wins, but this only tells half of the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there have been many successful modern digital services released in Canada, there are also years-long initiatives that don’t ever seem to ship, and motivated teams who end up stalled or burnt out under reams of &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/articles/2021-12-13-paperweight/&quot;&gt;onerous oversight&lt;/a&gt;. All to say, there are &lt;em&gt;plenty&lt;/em&gt; of lessons being learned across government that would be helpful to share with other culturally-aligned teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; about criticizing specific individuals or committees, leaking secret or upcoming projects, or for commenting on government policies. Rather, my intent is to highlight structural tendencies and patterns of behaviour, and to uncover issues or propose possible strategies that may, ultimately, help to create a more reponsive government, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gds.blog.gov.uk/2011/07/29/welcome-to-the-government-digital-service-blog/&quot;&gt;relentlessly focused on user needs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sboots&quot;&gt;Sean Boots&lt;/a&gt; has a great blog post &lt;a href=&quot;https://sboots.ca/2020/01/21/principles-for-blogging-as-a-public-servant/&quot;&gt;on blogging as a public servant&lt;/a&gt;, where he effectively sums up the goal as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach I want to champion is: openly criticizing things that are systemically broken, while still acting with the respect and integrity that public servants are meant to embody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is to say, it’s not about airing dirty laundry, more about pointing out how the washing machine shreds all of our good shirts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that sounds interesting to you, give it a try and subscribe &lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;👇&lt;/span&gt;. If not, well, you should subscribe anyway: you will rarely get emails from me and &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/pages/about/#what-happens-if-i-subscribe&quot;&gt;you just might win an iPod&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have feedback, or want to leave a comment? I couldn’t figure out how to set up commenting with eleventy (might do it later if comments are something people want), but I have opened up &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pcraig3/fed-notes/discussions&quot;&gt;Discussions in the Github repo&lt;/a&gt;. Feel free to leave a comment in there, or you can always &lt;a href=&quot;https://federal-field-notes.ca/pages/contact&quot;&gt;Contact me&lt;/a&gt; directly.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>